Guide to the John Browne, Commonplace Book
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
[Commonplace book].
1680-1680
OSBORN FB155
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.27
(1 volume)
Copies of Parliamentary papers, including speeches, orders, petitions, and declarations. Most printed in Lords Journals or in Rushworth. Includes items from parliaments of Elizabeth I through James II, most between 1630-1680.
Browne, John, approximately 1608-1691
Immediate Source of Acquisition
For provenance information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The following finding aid is a complete inventory of the contents of Osborn fb155. This list was reformatted from previously existing cataloging.
Law -- Great Britain; Nobility -- Great Britain; Great Britain -- Court and courtiers; Great Britain -- Foreign relations -- Spain; Great Britain -- Politics and government -- 1558-1603; Great Britain -- Politics and government -- 1603-1714; Great Britain -- Religious life and customs -- 17th century; Spain -- Foreign relations -- Great Britain; Commonplace books; Charles, King of England, I, 1600-1649; Elizabeth, Queen of England, I, 1533-1603; Henrietta Maria, Queen, consort of Charles I, King of England, 1609-1669; James, King of England, I, 1566-1625; Browne, John, approximately 1608-1691; Buckingham, George Villiers, Duke of, 1592-1628; Great Britain. Parliament; Order of the Garter; Braye, Alfred Verney-Cave, Baron, 1849-1928 -- Bookplate
- Osborn fb155 (Volume 1)
  - JAMES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1566-1625
    - [Speeches to Parliament, 5 & 8 April 1614], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      Scope and Contents
      12 p.
      MS copy in the hand of John Browne.
      On elections, religion, and supply.
      Printed in Cobbett's Parliamentary
      History, vi, 1149.
      p.1-12.
  - JAMES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1566-1625
    - [Commission to Sir John Digby to be an ambassador to Spain, 1617 April 16] (Volume 1)
      2 p.
      MS copy.
      Commission to John Digby, 1st earl of
      Bristol (1580-1653) to negotiate for
      a Spanish match for Prince Charles.
      p.13-14.
  - GREAT BRITAIN, COURT OF STAR CHAMBER
    - "The heads of the charges against Earl of Oxford" c. Apr 1622, [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      1 p.
      Henry de Vere, 18th earl of Oxford
      (1593-1635) charged with attacks on
      the King's government.
      p.15.
  - GREAT BRITAIN, PRIVY COUNCIL.
    - "At the Court in Whitehall, 15 Jan 1620", [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      Appointment of a commission to
      consider the recovery of the
      Palatinate.
      p.16-17.
  - DORSET, EDWARD SACKVILLE, 4TH EARL OF, 1591-1652
    - [Speech in the House of Commons urging that subsidies be given for the recovery of the Palatinate, 1621 Nov 26] (Volume 1)
      6 p.
      MS copy. Rushworth, vi, 131.
      (Rushworth incorrectly attributes the
      speech to 1623; see DNB).
      p.17-22.
  - WIMBLEDON, SIR EDWARD CECIL, 1ST VISCOUNT, 1572-1638
    - [Speech in the House of Commons, 5 Feb 1620/1], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      Urges Commons to grant supply for
      the recovery of the Palatinate.
      Calendared in CSPD, 1619-1623, p.220
      Gardiner, in "History of England",
      v.4, p.29, claims that this speech
      is a forgery.
      p.23-28.
  - PERROT, SIR JAMES, 1517-1637
    - "A true copie of the motion made in the Commons house of Parliament the 14th of June 1621. By Sir James Perrot, Knt...", [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      4 p.
      A report of Perrot's speech
      supporting true religion and the
      Palatinate and a copy of the
      Declaration passed by the Commons on
      these same issues. Rushworth, I, 36
      (Declaration), Cobbett's
      Parliamentary History, vi, 1293
      (speech).
      p.29-32.
  - JAMES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1566-1625
    - [Letter to the Speaker of the House of Commons warning Parliament not to meddle in matters under the royal prerogative, 1621 Dec 3] (Volume 1)
      MS copy. Rushworth, I, 43.
      p.33-34.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1621. HOUSE OF COMMONS
    - [Petition and remonstrance to King James I against the spread of popery, 1621 Dec 8] (Volume 1)
      MS copy. Rushworth, I, 40.
      p.35-40.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1621. HOUSE OF COMMONS
    - [Remonstrance or Apology sent to King James I, 1621 Dec 8], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      5 p.
      Explanation of Parliament's actions.
      Rushworth, I, 44.
      p.41-45.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1621. HOUSE OF COMMONS
    - [Heads for a petitions for the better execution of laws against seminary priests and Popish recusants, c Dec 1621] (Volume 1)
      Measures against Catholics.
      p.46-47.
  - JAMES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1566-1625
    - [Answer to the petition of the House of Commons concerning its privileges, 1621 Dec 12], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      11 p.
      MS copy. Rushworth, I, 46.
      p.48-59.
  - JAMES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1566-1625
    - [The King's letter to Secretary Calvert to be conveyed to the House of Commons, 1621 Dec 16], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      3 p.
      Clarification of an earlier message
      on the Commons privileges (see
      p.48-59 this volume). Cobbett's
      Parliamentary History, v.i, 1350.
      p.60-62.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1621. HOUSE OF COMMONS
    - [The Protestation of the House of Commons concerning its privileges, 1621 Dec 18], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      MS copy. Rushworth, I, 53.
      p.63-64.
  - JAMES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1566-1625
    - "His Majesty's letter to the Speaker, 17 Dec 1621", [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      Threatens to dismiss Parliament if
      members refuse to return to business.
      Cobbett's Parliamentary History, v.i,
      1355.
      p.65-66.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1621. HOUSE OF COMMONS
    - [Petition to the King for a recess rather than an adjournment, 1621 Dec 18] (Volume 1)
      1359. Followed by the King's reply,
      19 Dec 1621 (p.68).
      p.67.
  - [ANONYMOUS]
    - [Newsletter], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      News of the Thirty Years' War and the
      English ambassador's (John Digby, 1st
      earl of Bristol) efforts to persuade
      the Emperor to restore the Palatinate
      to the elector, Frederick.
      p.69-74.
  - FERDINAND II, EMPEROR OF GERMANY, 1578-1637
    - [Letter to James I, 1621/2 Jan 14], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      MS copy. In Latin.
      p.75.
  - WILLIAMS, JOHN, ABP. OF YORK, 1582-1650
    - "A speech of Lord Keeper Williams in Chancery, 9 Oct 1621", [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      8 p.
      His speech upon assuming office,
      apologizing for his inexperience in
      law and setting forth his intentions.
      Includes comments on the law of
      equity and on lawyers.
      p.76-83.
  - JAMES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1566-1625
    - "King James answer to King Fernando, 12 Nov 1621" (Volume 1)
      5p.
      Proposals of peace to end the
      Bohemian Wars. Ferdinand II, Emperor
      of Germany, 1578-1637. Friedrich I,
      King of Bohemia and Elector Palatine,
      1596-1632. Thirty Years' War.
      p.84-88.
  - YELVERTON, SIR HENRY, 1566-1629
    - [Speech of Submission in Star Chamber, 1620 Oct 27], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      Acknowledges his fault in the matter
      of the Charter for London.
      Calendared under this date in CSPD,
      1619-1623, p.186. MS is dated "Nov
      1620".
      p.92.
  - CHARLES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1600-1649
    - [Speech to Parliament asking for supply for the War in the Palatinate, 1625 June 18], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      MS copy. LJ, III, 435.
      p.93-94.
  - WILLIAMS, JOHN, ABP. OF YORK, 1582-1650
    - [The Lord Keeper's Speech to Parliament of the need for subsidies for the war in the Palatinate, 1625 June 18], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      MS copy. LJ, III, 436.
      f.94-96.
  - CREWE, SIR THOMAS, 1565-1634
    - [The speech of the Speaker of the House of Commons at his presentation to the King, 1625 June 20], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      7 p.
      Also the speech of acceptance of the
      Speaker by the Lord Keeper.
      LJ, III, 437 (in part).
      f.96-102.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1625.
    - "A Petition delivered from both houses of Parliament to his Majesty... 1625 June 24" (Volume 1)
      Petition for a day of fast and
      repentance. Reported in Cobbett's
      Parliamentary History, v.2, p 5.
      p.103.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1625.
    - [The petition of both houses against papists, 1625 July 6], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      MS copy. LJ, III, 419 (with the
      King's answers).
      p.104-109.
  - COKE, SIR EDWARD, 1552-1634
    - [Speech in Parliament, 1625 Aug 5], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      Demands the King undertake financial
      reform rather than depending on
      subsidies from Parliament. Reported
      in Cobbett's Parliamentary History,
      v.2, p.12.
      p.110-112.
  - CHARLES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1600-1649
    - [Speech to the Parliament meeting at Oxford asking for supply to carry out the War for the recovery of the Palatinate, 1625 Aug 14], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      Followed by the speeches of the
      King's ministers, Lord Conway and Sir
      John Coke, declaring the state of the
      King's affairs. LJ, III, 1470.
      p.113-117.
  - BUCKINGHAM, GEORGE VILLIERS, 1ST DUKE OF, 1592-1628
    - [Speech to Parliament, 1625 Aug 8], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      10 p.
      A short introductory speech by Lord
      Keeper Williams on the petition
      against papists (see p.128-130 this
      volume), followed by Buckingham's
      speech on war preparations.
      Rushworth, I, 188.
      p.118-127.
  - CHARLES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1600-1649
    - [Answer to Parliament's petition against papists, 1625 Aug 8], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      MS copy. LJ, III, 479.
      p.128-130.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1625. HOUSE OF COMMONS
    - [Declaration of the House of Commons to the King protesting Parliament's loyalty upon the dismissal of the Oxford Parliament, 1625 Aug 12], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      MS copy. Rushworth, 1, p.170.
      p.131.
  - [ANONYMOUS]
    - "An Advertisement to a Friende" [c 1625 Aug] (Volume 1)
      Newsletter on the dissolution of the
      Oxford Parliament and their
      discontent. Includes comments on the
      designs of George Villiers, 1st
      duke of Buckingham (1592-1628) and
      the opposition of Sir Robert Mansell
      (1573-1656).
      p.132-133.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. TREATIES
    - [Articles of marriage between the Elector Palatine and the Princess Elizabeth, c.1612] (Volume 1)
      Elizabeth of England, consort of
      Frederick I, 1596-1662.
      p.134-136.
  - GREGORIUS XV, POPE, 1554-1623
    - [Letter to the Bishop of Corches, Inquisitor-general in Spain, 1623 April 19] (Volume 1)
      p.137-138.
  - CHARLES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1600-1649
    - [The Prince of England's letter to Pope Gregory on the Spanish Match, 1623 July 8] (Volume 1)
      Pope Gregorius XV, 1554-1623. A
      different version of this letter is
      printed in Rushworth, v.i, 82, dated
      1623 June 20.
      p.139-140.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. TREATIES.
    - [Marriage treaty between Charles I and Henrietta Maria, 1624 Nov 30] (Volume 1)
      Articles of marriage including
      provisions for the dowry and
      religious concessions made to
      Henrietta Maria, Queen Consort of
      Charles I, 1609-1669.
      p.141-147.
  - JAMES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1566-1625
    - [Speech to Parliament asking for advice on foreign affairs, 1623/4 Feb 19], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      MS copy. LJ, III, 209.
      p.148-151.
  - WILLIAMS, JOHN, ABP. OF YORK, 1582-1650
    - [The Lord Keeper's speech to Parliament, 1623/4 Feb 19], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      Praises King James' speech at the
      opening of Parliament.
      p.151-152.
  - BUCKINGHAM, GEORGE VILLIERS, 1ST DUKE OF, 1592-1628
    - [Report of the Duke's speech to Parliament, 1623/4 Feb 24], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      13 p.
      Report on the Spanish marriage
      negotiations. LJ, III, 220.
      p.152-164.
  - CREWE, SIR THOMAS, 1565-1634
    - [The speech of the Speaker of the House of Commons at his presentation; the speech of the Lord Keeper, 1623/4 Feb 21] (Volume 1)
      MS copy. LJ, III, 211.
      p.165-175.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1624.
    - [Conference between two houses, 1623/4 Mar 2], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      Concerning the breaking off of the
      Spanish treaties. Speeches by John
      Williams, Abp. of York and Lord
      Keeper, George Abbott, Abp. of
      Canterbury, and Sir Edward Coke. The
      two houses agree to advise the King
      to break off the treaties.
      LJ, III, 242.
      p.176-180.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1624.
    - [The reasons of the House of Commons for breaking off the Spanish treaties, with additional reasons added by the House of Lords, 1623/4 Mar 5], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      MS copy. LJ, III, 246.
      p.181-183.
  - FELIPE IV, KING OF SPAIN, 1605-1665
    - [Letter to Gaspar de Guzman, Conde-duque de Olivares (1587-1645) on the marriage negotiations with the Prince of Wales, 1622 Nov 5] (Volume 1)
      MS copy. In English.
      LJ, III, 226.
      p.183-184.
  - OLIVARES, GASPAR DE GUZMAN, CONDE-DUQUE DE, 1587-1645
    - [Letter to Felipe IV, King of Spain, about the marriage alliance with England, 1622 Nov 8] (Volume 1)
      In response to the King's letter
      (see p.183).
      p.184-188.
  - PORTLAND, RICHARD WESTON, 1ST EARL OF, 1577-1635
    - "Collections out of Sir Richard Weston's report to the lower House 1623/4 March 4", [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      Report on the trip of George
      Villiers, 1st duke of Buckingham, and
      Charles I, King of Great Britain,
      into Spain.
      p.188-191.
  - COTTINGTON, FRANCIS COTTINGTON, 1ST BARON, 1578?-1652
    - [Report to Parliament, 1623/4 March 4], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      Report on the Spanish journey and
      negotiations for the Spanish
      marriage.
      p.191-193.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1624.
    - [Message to the King advising him to break off the Spanish treaties, 1623/4 Mar 5], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      MS copy. LJ, III, 250.
      p.194.
  - JAMES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1566-1625
    - [Answer to the Parliament's message concerning the breaking off of the Spanish treaties, 1623/4 Mar 5], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      p.195-199.
  - CHARLES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1600-1649
    - "The Prince his Speech to a Committee of both houses, 11 March 1623[-4]", [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      Clarification of his father's speech
      on subsidies and war with Spain.
      LJ, III, 257.
      p.200-201.
  - JAMES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1566-1625
    - [Speech to Parliament on the war to recover the Palatinate, 1623/4 Mar 14], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      MS copy. LJ, III, 265.
      p.202-206.
  - BUCKINGHAM, GEORGE VILLIERS, 1ST DUKE OF, 1592-1628
    - [Speech to Parliament, 1623/4 March 1 or 17], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      On the Spanish marriage, Spain and
      the Palatinate. Dated both 15 and 17
      March.
      p.207-209.
  - JAMES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1566-1625
    - [A summary of the King's letter to Parliament affirming his willingness to break off the Spanish treaties, 1623/4 Mar 17], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      MS copy (summary).
      The complete letter is printed in LJ,
      III, 265.
      p.210.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1624.
    - "Articles to be seen into speedily" [c.1623/4 March], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      Articles concern the defenses of the
      Kingdom, the armed forces, and steps
      to be taken against Catholics.
      p.211.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1624.
    - [The speech at the presentation of the subsidies, 1623/4 Mar 23], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      Promise the King support in war
      against Spain. LJ, III, 275.
      p.212-214.
  - JAMES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1566-1625
    - [Answer to Parliament's petition on breaking off the Spanish treaties, 1623/4 March 23], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      Agrees to break treaties.
      LJ, III, 282.
      p.214-215.
  - CREWE, SIR THOMAS, 1565-1634
    - [Speech of the Speaker at the prorogation of Parliament, 1624 May 28], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      MS copy. LJ, III, 423.
      p.216-222.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. TREATIES, 1603-1625 (JAMES I)
    - "A Brief of the Articles of the League between the Kings of France, England, the Commonwealth of Venice, and the Duke of Savoy" [1624] (Volume 1)
      Defensive and offensive league
      against the Spanish.
      p.223-224.
  - NORTHUMBERLAND, HENRY PERCY, 9TH EARL OF, 1564-1632
    - [The Earl of Northumberland's discourse on the proceedings between himself and Sir Francis Vere, 1602 April 23] (Volume 1)
      Northumberland's account of his
      differences with Sir Francis Vere
      (1560-1609) and his attempt to settle
      them by a duel. The duel was
      prevented by Vere's refusal and the
      Queen's order.
      p.225-230.
  - BOLEYN, ANNE, CONSORT OF HENRY VIII, 1507-1536
    - "Queen Anne Bollens letter to King Henry the 8th found among Cromwell's Papers [1536] May 6" (Volume 1)
      MS copy. Asks for a lawful trial to
      prove her innocence.
      p.231-233.
  - ELIZABETH I, QUEEN OF ENGLAND, 1533-1603
    - [Message to the House of Commons on unruly members, 1571 May 27], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      MS copy. Cobbett, i, 766.
      p.234-235.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. SOVEREIGNS, ETC., 1603-1625 (JAMES I)
    - [Proclamations, 1610 March 25], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      A proclamation for the calling in of
      "The Interpretor" by Dr. John Cowell
      (1554-1611), due to its harmful
      effects towards both the King and
      Parliament.
      p.235-237.
  - MAYNARD, SIR JOHN, 1602-1690
    - [Letter to "one about the King", London, 1648 August] (Volume 1)
      Newsletter on events in London,
      Parliament, and the Army. The letter
      was apparently not sent.
      p.237-239.
  - CHARLES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1600-1649
    - [The King's reasons for declining the jurisdiction of the High Court of Justice, 1648/9 Jan 21], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      Rushworth, v.7, 1403.
      p.239-243.
  - LONDON. MINISTERS.
    - [Queries concerning the oath by the 6th canon (the etcetera oath), ca. 1640], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      Questions the legality and meaning of
      the Etcetera Oath of 1640.
      p.243-247.
  - ANDERSON, SIR EDMUND, 1530-1605
    - [Legal writings concerning imprisonment without causes shown, ca. late 16th century], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      MS copy (extracts).
      On habeas corpus and other legal
      remedies.
      p.247-252.
  - WESTMINSTER ASSEMBLY OF DIVINES
    - "Declaration against the Blasphemous opinions in Mr. Archer's book, by the Assembly of Divines and by the authority of parliament" [1645 July 17] (Volume 1)
      A refutation of Archer's blasphemy
      that God is the author of all sin.
      Printed in 1645. John Archer,
      Preacher of All Hallows, Lombard St.,
      Comfort for all believers.
      p.252-255.
  - OXFORD UNIVERSITY
    - "Protestation of the Doctors of Oxford, 1641/2 Feb 18", [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      Declaration of loyalty to Church and
      King. Followed by a list of
      supporters and opponents of the
      Protestation.
      p.245-257.
  - HENRIETTA MARIA, QUEEN CONSORT OF CHARLES I
    - [Protestation to the States General of the Low Countries on her Majesty's departure from Scheveling, 1643 Feb 25], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      Complains of her treatment, the
      arrest of her ship, and the refusal
      of the States General to aid Charles
      I. The Protestation was issued by the
      English resident Sir William Boswell
      (d.1649) on order of the Queen.
      p.257-258.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1643
    - "An answer intended by both houses to be sent to the King April 1643 but not sent" (Volume 1)
      Objections to King Charles the 1st's
      terms for peace.
      p.259-264.
  - [ANONYMOUS]
    - [The oath of the clerk of parliament], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      MS copy [17th century].
      p.264.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. ARMY. COUNCIL.
    - [Proposals sent by the general and Council of the Army to the commissioners of Parliament, 1647 Aug 1] (Volume 1)
      Proposals for reforms in the
      government, parliament, etc.
      Rushworth, v.7, 731.
      p.264-277.
  - CHARLES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1600-1649
    - [Grant to Murrough O'Brien Inchiquin, 1st earl and 6th baron of Munster, Ireland (1614-1674), and instructions to the Lord President, 1644/5 Jan 14] (Volume 1)
      The appointment is made with the
      "advise and consent of Parliament."
      The instructions concern governmental
      and military duties. London, 1641.
      p.277-283.
  - CHARLES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1600-1649
    - "The Kings manifest touching the Palatine Cause" [1641], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      Summary of England's past support of
      the Palatinate and a declaration that
      King Charles will attempt once again
      to treat for peace at the Diet of
      Ratisbon. Printed in London, 1641.
      p.283-288.
  - SWEDEN. SOVEREIGNS, 1632-1654 (CHRISTIANA)
    - [Propositions of the Queen of Sweden's commissioners to the Parliament of England, and the answers of Parliament, 1645 Mar 31] (Volume 1)
      9 p.
      Swedish request for aid in their War
      against the Danes and the Emperor.
      p.288-296.
  - SCOTLAND. COMMISSIONERS IN LONDON, 1646
    - [Letter to the English Parliament, 1645/6 Jan 24], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      Complaint of false accusations
      against the Army and Kingdom of
      Scotland. LJ, VIII, 123.
      p.296-302.
  - BROWNE, JOHN, D.1691
    - [Forms of direction for royal letters], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      Autograph MS [17th century].
      Proper addresses for Barons, Dukes,
      Bishops, etc.
      p.303.
  - BROWNE, JOHN, D.1691
    - [List of Cathedral and Collegiate Churches in England and Wales] (Volume 1)
      List divided into churches of the
      old and the new foundations.
      p.304-305.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1649. HOUSE OF COMMONS
    - "An Act for erecting a High Court of Justice for trying and judging of James Earl of Cambridge, Henry Earl of Holland, George Lord Goring, Arthur Lord Capel, and Sir John Owen." [1648/9 Feb 3] (Volume 1)
      The prisoners are accused of levying
      civil war against Parliament. James
      Hamilton, 2nd earl of Cambridge
      (1608-1649); Henry Rich, 1st earl of
      Holland (1590-1649); George Goring,
      baron (1608-1657); Arthur Capel,
      baron (1610?-1649); Sir John Owen
      (1600-1666).
      p.306-308.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. HIGH COURT OF JUSTICE.
    - [Order to the Sheriff of Middlesex to carry out the sentence against James Earl of Cambridge, 1648/9 Mar 6], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      The Earl was convicted of treason
      and sentenced to death.
      Document includes list of the judges
      and a note that the same sentence was
      passed against the Earl of Holland
      and Lord Capel.
      p.308-309.
  - JAMES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1566-1625
    - [Instructions for Viscount Falkland on his appointment as lord deputy of Ireland, 1622 Aug 4] (Volume 1)
      Contemporary MS copy (signed "Copia
      Veria, H.Falkland, Geo.Calvert").
      Ordered to take special care of
      religion, the settlement of land,
      and the King's revenues. Henry Cary,
      1st viscount Falkland, d.1633
      George Calvert, 1st lord Baltimore
      (1580?-1632).
      p.310-320.
  - ORDER OF THE GARTER
    - [Statutes and ordinances of the Order of the Garter, as reformed by Henry VIII, with additions by Philip and Mary, 16th century] (Volume 1)
      34 p.
      Rules, customs, officers, etc. of
      the Order.
      p.321-354.
  - CHARLES II, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1630-1685
    - [Grant to Sir Richard Browne (bart., c.1605-1683) of the office of Muster Master General, 1682 Mar 30], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      p.355.
  - BROWNE, JOHN, D.1691